A Guide to the Fairfax County Road Petitions, 1844-1908
Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
Fairfax County Road Petitions, 1844-1908, 1844-1854, 1856-1858, 1866-1908, non-inclusive
Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
5 linear feet.
Fairfax Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Permanent Records of Fairfax Circuit Court
Biographical Information
Fairfax County was founded in 1742 from the northern part of Prince William County. Public transportation was, and continues to be, vital to Fairfax County's economy. Using the Code of Virginia, one can better understand how roads were authorized and developed.
Prior to the Byrd Road Act of 1932, roads were authorized by the court, and in the early 20th century, the Board of Supervisors. According to Chapter LII of the 1860 Virginia Code, once a person applied for a county road to be opened or changed, the court proceeded by appointing road commissioners and otherwise ascertaining the practicality and usefulness of the proposed road, the benefit to the community and individual, and any damages to surrounding property. To establish any one road, no more than one acre could be taken from a single individual. The road proposed is usually identified as being the road from "Point A" to "Point B," the points being known areas of interest, i.e. mills, churches, stores, dams, turnpikes, and so on.
First, the circuit court received an application for a county road, usually from an individual with anywhere between one and upwards of 30 fellow petitioners. The court then directed one or more of the county's road commissioners to view the proposed land for the road and its surroundings and then report on the conveniences and inconveniences to both individuals and the public - especially if any yard, garden, or orchard needed to be taken for the proposed road. The commissioner's job was to report facts and circumstances that would help the court determine the expediency of establishing or altering the county road. The commissioner(s) could also offer their opinion either in favor of or against the proposed road and suggest alternate routes. A map, plat, or diagram had to accompany the road commissioner(s) report, and if the commissioner was not a surveyor, one had to be procured.
Citizens could also apply to discontinue a road, though it was far rarer. To do so, the person had to publish a notice of the intended application on the first day of the county court's term at the county courthouse door and in two public places in the neighborhood.
After it received all the reports and other evidence, the court then determined whether the road would be established or altered as proposed and who would maintain it.
Once the court received the commissioner's report, provided it was favorable to the proposed road, the court summoned the proprietors and tenants of the lands affected by the proposed road. Once the sheriff executed the summons, the court determined the matter of the road without a writ of ad quod damnum if the court had enough funds for a just compensation and if the proprietors and tenants accepted the compensation. (A writ of ad quod damnum is a law term from the English chancery ordering the sheriff to determine what damages a certain act will incur). But if any proprietor or tenant wished for a writ or the court saw good cause for it, the court awarded it. The writ of ad quod damnum commanded the sheriff to summon a jury of twelve freeholders to meet on the proprietors' and tenants' lands, view them, and ascertain a just compensation for the land damages. The jury also ascertained if the proposed road was one of more private convenience and, accordingly, if a lesser compensation was appropriate.
Once the court received the commissioner's report, provided it was favorable to the proposed road, the court summoned the proprietors and tenants of the lands affected by the proposed road. Once the sheriff executed the summons, the court determined the matter of the road without a writ of ad quod damnum if the court had enough funds for a just compensation and if the proprietors and tenants accepted the compensation. (A writ of ad quod damnum is a law term from the English chancery ordering the sheriff to determine what damages a certain act will incur). But if any proprietor or tenant wished for a writ or the court saw good cause for it, the court awarded it. The writ of ad quod damnum commanded the sheriff to summon a jury of twelve freeholders to meet on the proprietors' and tenants' lands, view them, and ascertain a just compensation for the land damages. The jury also ascertained if the proposed road was one of more private convenience and, accordingly, if a lesser compensation was appropriate.
Scope and Content
This collection starts in 1844 and ends in 1908. The bulk of the collection is concentrated from 1867 through 1890, with a particularly prominent concentration from 1886 through 1890. No records from 1859 through 1865 exist. Likewise, no road petition records exist prior to 1844 - both gaps in chronology are likely due to military activity during the Civil War. The Library of Virginia identifies Fairfax County as a "Lost Records Locality," meaning this locality suffered significant losses of early records due to military action. Our records end in 1908 because the law changed in 1909, shifting responsibility for road petitions to the county's Board of Supervisors.
Most road petition folders include court summons and/or the original petition. These petitions usually include original signatures. Many also include reports from district road commissioners, plats, and letters of correspondence to the court. The reports from the road commissioners and the court summons are the most common documents, while the plats and letters are slightly rarer.
In addition to the main petitioner, month and year of the petition, and the road in question, each folder notes any additional petitioners if applicable and neighbors around the proposed road. The neighbors are particularly useful to see who lived near who, and how that changed over time. Some neighbor listings note someone's heirs, which indicates the property owner is deceased and their heirs owned the property. If a plat is included, it is noted on the folder and in the index.
One person of note from this collection is Margaret Hetzel. Her name appears in eight road petitions either as a main petitioner, an additional petitioner, or a neighbor. She appears to have been very active in the Fairfax community, even into her old age as her health declined and kept her from appearing in court. Her main concern in these road petitions was road safety. In several of the cases, she wrote directly to the judge urging him to grant the road petition because the existing road or route was unsafe. She expressed concern over a very high hill, decaying bridges, and deeply rutted roads. And in road cases in 1892, 1893 and 1897, she freely gave her land and did not claim any damages. She seems to have been a woman committed to improving her community and far more involved in doing so than we might expect for the average 19th century woman.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically by the year the petition was made, and then alphabetically by the main petitioner within each year.
Index Terms
Richardson, F. D. (1808-1880); Fairfax Circuit Court; Roads, transportation, railroads, road repairs, road safety; Fairfax County, Virginia; Paper, iron gall ink, graphite pencil, watercolor; Clerk of Circuit Court
Contents List
- July, 1844. (Box-folder 1: RP-001)
  Road leading from old Pohick Church to the Stage Road at Occoquan.
- June, 1844 (Box-folder RP-002)
  Change: Road leading by Gunston House (Tea Table) to Hallowing Point
- August, 1844 (Box-folder RP-003)
  Change: Hunter's Mill Road beginning at Old Courthouse Road
- October, 1844 (Box-folder RP-004)
  Change: Middle Turnpike to the Falls Church
- April, 1845 (Box-folder RP-005)
  Road from Fairfax Court House to McIlhaney's Toll Gate
- May, 1845 (Box-folder RP-006)
  Road from Fox's Upper Mill to German Town
- July, 1845 (Box-folder RP-007)
  From Hunter's Mill Road to the Little River Turnpike Road
- March, 1845 (Box-folder RP-008)
  Change: road leading to Fairfax County Courthouse near N. Cornell's blacksmith shop
- June, 1845 (Box-folder RP-009)
  Road beginning at Ellzey's Church Road...to the road leading from Fairfax Courthouse to the Old Courthouse
- November, 1845 (Box-folder RP-010)
  Between difficult bridge on the Middle Turnpike Road and Mateers Tavern
- August, 1846 (Box-folder RP-011)
  Road beginning at a point on the Falls Church Road to the Falls Bridge Turnpike Road
- February, 1847 (Box-folder RP-012)
  Change: road from Middle Turnpike to the Union Meeting House
- March, 1848 (Box-folder RP-013)
  Road leading from Ball's Neighborhood to Middle Turnpike
- July, 1848 (Box-folder RP-014)
  Road from lands of Devaughn to the Rolling Road
- August, 1848 (Box-folder RP-015)
  Change: the Falls Road
- January, 1848 (Box-folder RP-016)
  Change: to the Wolf Run Shoals Road
- February, 1848 (Box-folder RP-017)
  Road from Newman on Horsepan Run...to road at Frying Pan Church
- April, 1848 (Box-folder RP-018)
  Change: part of Hunter's Mill Road
- January, 1849
  Change: Backlick Road to the Rolling Road
- July, 1849 (Box-folder RP-020)
  Change: Conn's Ferry Road
- March, 1850 (Box-folder RP-021)
  Change: Pohick Church to Mason's Neck
- March, 1850 (Box-folder RP-022)
  Road from intersection of road leading from Accotink Mills...to the Backlit Road
- October, 1851 (Box-folder RP-023)
  Survey of boundary line between Brook and Williams
- September, 1851 (Box-folder RP-024)
  Road from Frying Pan Church to Liberty Church
- January, 1851 (Box-folder RP-025)
  Road from Backlick Road to the Middle Turnpike Road
- January, 1851 (Box-folder RP-026)
  Road from Dranesville to Potomac at/or near where J.R.M. Lowe's sawmill formerly stood (Lowe's Island)
- July, 1851 (Box-folder RP-027)
  Change: Road leading to Shirley Gate
- November, 1851
  Road from Stage Road near foot of Potter's Hill...to Backlick Road
- June, 1851 (Box-folder RP-029)
  Road from Little River Turnpike to intersect the road leading from the Frying Pan Road
- March, 1852 (Box-folder RP-030)
  Road from point on Frying Pan Road at Gunnells School House to Liberty Church at Dranesville
- July, 1852 (Box-folder RP-031)
  Road from Falls Church Road...to the old Backlit Road
- July, 1853 (Box-folder RP-032)
  Change: Road leading from Alexandria County Line to the Middle Turnpike
- March, 1854 (Box-folder RP-033)
  Road at the new cut road near house of John Fox...to Fox's Mill Road
- April, 1856 (Box-folder RP-034)
  Road from land of J. Edward Chase...to the Telegraph Road
- October, 1856 (Box-folder RP-035)
  Road through lands of F.F. Triplett...to Rolling Road; Referred in Appeal of Bond vs. Green et. al. Supreme Court of Virginia Appeals - 7 March 1949 (189 va. 23)
- March, 1856 (Box-folder RP-036)
  Change: road leading from Falls Church Road to the Little River Turnpike
- April, 1856 (Box-folder RP-037)
  Road from F.F. Triplett's to the Rolling Road
- May, 1857 (Box-folder RP-038)
  Road from Stryker's Land...to road leading to Fairfax Courthouse
- May, 1858 (Box-folder RP-039)
  Town of Colchester from lot #15 to lot #8 - following a street as laid down
- February, 1866 (Box-folder RP-040)
  Road from the Ox Road to Fairfax Court House
- April, 1866 (Box-folder RP-041)
  Change: road from Follin's Corner to the Old Court House
- August, 1866 (Box-folder RP-042)
  Change: County Road near Union Mills
- May, 1866 (Box-folder RP-043)
  Road from the Friends Meeting House to the Telegraph Road through Warrington Gillingham's farm
- November, 1866 (Box-folder RP-044)
  Close road leading from the Little River Turnpike to the Old Church
- November, 1866 (Box-folder RP-045)
  Road from Harrison's Crossing on the Orange and Alexandria Railroad to some point near Fairfax Station
- March, 1866 (Box-folder RP-046)
  Road from Nancy Kidwell's farm on Guinea Road to the Railroad at London's Mill
- May, 1967 (Box-folder RP-047)
  Petition to assess condition of First and Second section of Middle Turnpike Road
- October, 1867 (Box-folder RP-047)
  Road from Centreville to Orange and Alexandria Railroad at Union Mills
- May, 1867 (Box-folder RP-049)
  Change: The Telegraph Road where it crosses Accotink Run
- April, 1867 (Box-folder RP-050)
  Change: "Windsor Road" - leading from Alexandria Road to the Telegraph Road
- April, 1867 (Box-folder RP-051)
  Road leading from New Cut Road to west side of Fox's Mill Dam
- May, 1867 (Box-folder RP-052)
  Road from Springfield Road to the Little River Turnpike
- January, 1867 (Box-folder RP-053)
  Change: "Lawyer's Road" near Hawxhurst Mill
- July, 1867 (Box-folder RP-054)
  Road leading from Neck County Road to the Alexandria, Accotink, and Mount Vernon Turnpike
- October, 1867 (Box-folder RP-055)
  Change: Route leading from Centreville and Frying Pan Road to the Little River Turnpike
- June, 1867 (Box-folder RP-056)
  The point on Falls Bridge Road...to New Cut Road
- October, 1967
  Road from John Pierson's Corner to Hunter's Mill Road
- August, 1867 (Box-folder RP-058)
  The Corner of Woodlawn Road to point near Mount Vernon Gate
- November, 1867 (Box-folder RP-059)
  Change: Road leading from Old Braddock Road to Payne's Church
- September, 1867 (Box-folder RP-060)
  Road through William Hunter's Property
- May, 1868 (Box-folder RP-061)
  Discontinue use of section of road leading from Guinea Road to Keene's Mill Road
- January, 1868 (Box-folder RP-062)
  Change: road leading from Annandale to Upton's Hill
- October, 1868 (Box-folder RP-063)
  Continuation of the Pole Road to Mount Vernon Road (Alexandria/Accotink Turnpike)
- April, 1868 (Box-folder RP-064)
  Discontinue section of New Market Road to Ball's Ford
- January, 1868 (Box-folder RP-065)
  Discontinue Road beginning at Colchester Road to the Neck Road
- June, 1868 (Box-folder RP-066)
  Road from Centreville to Devereau Station on the Orange and Alexandria Railroad
- September, 1868 (Box-folder RP-067)
  Change: Road leading from Colchester to Accotink Valley
- May, 1868 (Box-folder RP-068)
  Discontinue section of road leading from Old Mill Landing on Dogue Creek over lands to Troth, Wright and Mason
- June, 1868 (Box-folder RP-069)
  Point on Hunter's Mill Road to Johnson's Crossing on the A. L. & H. Railroad
- April, 1869 (Box-folder RP-070)
  Commencing on Brush's Land to the road leading from Falls Church to Fairfax Courthouse
- June, 1869 (Box-folder RP-071)
  Continuation of Road near Benjamin Shreve's house to the Gallow's Road
- February, 1869 (Box-folder RP-072)
  Braddock Road near intersection with Washburn's Land to Little River Turnpike (Old Alexandria Road)
- April, 1869 (Box-folder RP-073)
  Old Courthouse Road to Hunter's Mill
- May, 1869 (Box-folder RP-074)
  Landing on Dogue Creek at Old Washington Mill to public road leading to Alexandria
- June, 1869 (Box-folder RP-075)
  Road from the Old Leesburg Road to Herndon at the A. L. and H. Railroad
- July, 1869 (Box-folder RP-076)
  Intersection of Vienna Road with the Old Court House Road and Hunter's Mill Road to Middle Turnpike Road
- February, 1869 (Box-folder RP-077)
  Road beginning at Yate's Ford Road to the Colchester Road
- October, 1869 (Box-folder RP-078)
  Middle Turnpike Road to Backlit Road
- March, 1869 (Box-folder RP-079)
  Clifton Station to Yates Road
- June, 1869 (Box-folder RP-080)
  Commencing at the gate of James M. Talbot to some point on the County Road to Alexandria
- January, 1870 (Box-folder RP-081)
  Garner's Mill Road to the Georgetown Pike
- May, 1870 (Box-folder RP-082)
  Flint Hill Road to intersection of Fairfax Courthouse and Georgetown Road
- December, 1870 (Box-folder RP-083)
  Telegraph Road to Colchester Road
- 1870 (Box-folder RP-084)
  Point on Backlick Road to Braddock Road
- August, 1870 (Box-folder RP-085)
  Change: Road from Clifton to Wolf Runs Shoals Road
- May, 1871 (Box-folder RP-086)
  From point on the road leading from Fall's Church to Fairfax Courthouse to a point on the Middle Turnpike
- April, 1871 (Box-folder RP-087)
  From Ox Road in Herndon to the Herndon Station - W. & O Railroad
- September, 1871 (Box-folder RP-088)
  Wolf Run Shoals Road to Thomas Fairfax's Land
- May, 1871 (Box-folder RP-089)
  Petition to take Little Falls Road from Falls Church to Alexandria County Line of Toll Road
- March, 1871 (Box-folder RP-090)
  Change: New Cut Road
- April, 1871 (Box-folder RP-091)
  Horsepen Run near Hight's Mill to Loudon County Line
- June, 1871 (Box-folder RP-092)
  Road from Clifton and Centreville Road to Little River Turnpike near Chantilly
- November, 1871 (Box-folder RP-093)
  Road from Clifton to the Union Mills Road
- May, 1871 (Box-folder RP-094)
  Change: Road leading from Fairfax Courthouse to Hawxhurst and Hunter's Mill
- March, 1871 (Box-folder RP-095)
  Road from Little River Turnpike at Ayers to the Old Braddock Road
- January, 1872 (Box-folder RP-096)
  Road from the Great Falls to Tenley S. Swink
- December, 1872 (Box-folder RP--097)
  Point on the Rolling Road to Little River Turnpike near Lebanon Church
- April, 1872 (Box-folder RP-098)
  Road leading from Buckleys School House to Little River Turnpike
- February, 1872 (Box-folder RP-099)
  Road from Accotink Mill Road to Railroad Station on Long Branch
- 1872 (Box-folder RP-100)
  Beginning on Neck (Sheridan's Point) Road to the Alexandria, Mount Vernon and Accotink Turnpike Roads
- November, 1872 (Box-folder RP-101)
  Road from J. Wells on Warrenton and Alexandria Turnpike to Sudley Mills
- June, 1873 (Box-folder RP-102)
  Road from Lewinsville to the Great Falls
- 1873 (Box-folder RP-103)
  Request by Talbot
- December, 1873 (Box-folder RP-104)
  Vandeusen Road to Fairfax/Loudon Line
- June, 1873 (Box-folder RP-105)
  Change: County Road running over Hardbowers Hill
- August, 1874 (Box-folder RP-106)
  Road from Accotink Run to the Keen's Mill Road
- March, 1874 (Box-folder RP-107)
  Point on Middle Turnpike near Falls Church Station to Four Mile Run
- June, 1874 (Box-folder RP-108)
  Change: Portion of Ox Road near Henderson Road
- December, 1874 (Box-folder RP-109)
  Change: Road arount Gantts Hill from Tyson's Corner to Lewinsville
- August, 1874 (Box-folder RP-110)
  Road from the Old Fredericksburg Road (Accotink Turnpike) to the Road leading from the Gum Spring to the Ferry Landing
- December, 1874 (Box-folder RP-111)
  Point one mile west from the village at Herndon to Loudon County Line
- May, 1874 (Box-folder RP-112)
  Change: Road known as Doctor Hunter's New Road
- July, 1874 (Box-folder RP-113)
  Road from Scott Farm on Potomac to Garner's Mill Road
- February, 1874 (Box-folder RP-114)
  Road in Vienna from the Foundry to the Georgetown Road
- April, 1874 (Box-folder RP-115)
  Road from Colchester Road to Braddock Road
- October, 1875 (Box-folder RP-116)
  Road from Dyer's Ford along Bull Run to Road leading to Fairfax Courthouse
- April, 1875 (Box-folder RP-117)
  Turn road over to Fairfax County
- December, 1875 (Box-folder RP-118)
  Road from Mrs. Evan's Ford on the Bull Run to the Yate's Ford Road
- May, 1875 (Box-folder RP-119)
  Beginning at Lawyer's Road and running to the New Cut Road
- December, 1876 (Box-folder RP-120)
  Road between the Occoquan Run and the Ox Road
- May, 1876 (Box-folder RP-121)
  Discontinue road from Keene's Mill Road to the Rolling Road
- June, 1876 (Box-folder RP-122)
  Road leading from Peter Pulman's on Telegraph Road to Hunting Creek Bridge Road
- August, 1877 (Box-folder RP-123)
  Road from Neck Road to Alexandria and Accotink Road
- February, 1876 (Box-folder RP-124)
  Change: Road from Centreville to Little River Turnpike to avoid heavy grade
- March, 1876 (Box-folder RP-125)
  Road from Dyers Ford through lands of Lewis Woodyard
- 1876 (Box-folder RP-126)
  Road beginning at Fitzhugh's gate on Ox Road to New County Road
- September, 1876 (Box-folder RP-127)
  Road from Pohick to Farr's Cross Roads
- May, 1877 (Box-folder RP-128)
  Little River Turnpike and County Road leading from Springfield Station on Virginia Midland Railroad
- May, 1877 (Box-folder RP-129)
  Ashford's corner at School House to Old Cherry Tree at Braddock Road
- September, 1877 (Box-folder RP-130)
  Road from Union Mill Road to Colchester Road
- May, 1877 (Box-folder RP-131)
  Colored schoolhouse on Lewinsville Road to Alexandria and Leesburg Turnpike
- April, 1873 (Box-folder RP-132)
  Road from Little River Turnpike to Old Warrenton Turnpike
- February, 1877 (Box-folder RP-133)
  Gate near Burke's Mill Road to point where Virginia Midland Railroad crosses the Rolling Road
- June, 1877 (Box-folder RP-134)
  Change: Rolling Road at Frobel's Hill
- August, 1877 (Box-folder RP-135)
  Beginning at the corner of Land of Smyth and James Hunter and running...to the county road.
- February, 1877 (Box-folder RP-136)
  Road from Johnson's Crossing on the W & O Railroad to the Lawyers Road
- September, 1877 (Box-folder RP-137)
  From point on Hunters Mill Road to William Walter's Mill
- December, 1877 (Box-folder RP-138)
  Road from Bull Run to Fox Mill
- January, 1878 (Box-folder RP-139)
  Road from the Colchester Road to the Newman Road
- January, 1878 (Box-folder RP-140)
  Road from the Falls Road to the Georgetown Pike
- October, 1878 (Box-folder RP-141)
  Little River Turnpike to county road at land of B. F. Shreve
- March, 1878 (Box-folder RP-142)
  Little River Turnpike to Orange & Alexandria Railroad at Skinner's Crossing
- March, 1879 (Box-folder RP-143)
  Courthouse road to the Ridge Road
- 1879 (Box-folder RP-144)
  Road from county road near Lewis Chapel to Telegraph Station on the Alexandria and Fredericksburg Railroad
- April, 1879 (Box-folder RP-145)
  Point of Road leading from Court House and Hunters Mill Road to Vienna near Murnanes's Gate
- December, 1879 (Box-folder RP-146)
  Change: Orcutt Road to point where it intersects with Maple Avenue
- November, 1879 (Box-folder RP-147)
  Road leading from Falkner's Shop on Leesburg Turnpike to Fall's Church
- January, 1879 (Box-folder RP-148)
  Change: Old Road over Holmes Run known as Barcroft Bridge
- July, 1879 (Box-folder RP-149)
  Road leading from Little River Turnpike to Backlick Road by Lebanon school house
- April, 1879 (Box-folder RP-150)
  Great Falls and Lewinsville Road to the Middle Turnpike
- July, 1880 (Box-folder RP-151)
  Ridge Road
- May, 1880 (Box-folder RP-152)
  Yates Ford Road from Clifton Station to Union Mills
- October, 1880 (Box-folder RP-153)
  Beginning at corner of the land of Smyth
- April, 1880 (Box-folder RP-154)
  Road from Gum Spring to the intersection with the Mount Vernon Lane
- April, 1880 (Box-folder RP-155)
  Road leading from Annandale to Springfield to the Little River Turnpike
- October, 1880 (Box-folder RP-156)
  Change: Orcutt Road
- 1880 (Box-folder RP-157)
  Change: Ridge Road from Alexandria Turnpike to Herndon Station
- September, 1880 (Box-folder RP-158)
  Road from the Old Union school house to the Alexandria Pike
- 1880 (Box-folder RP-159)
  Road from Lincolnville to the Chain Bridge Road
- August, 1880 (Box-folder RP-160)
  Road beginning at the Alexandria Turnpike to the Falls Road
- 1880 (Box-folder RP-161)
  Public Highway from Andrew Chapel to Jackson Mill
- March, 1881 (Box-folder RP-162)
  Road from Hasbrook corner to Waples Mill Road
- February, 1881 (Box-folder RP-163)
  Point on the Newman Road to County Road to Herndon
- August, 1881
  Road from Little River Turnpike to Centreville and Frying Pan Road
- December, 1881 (Box-folder RP-165)
  Road from Braddock Road to Pohick Road
- 1882 (Box-folder RP-166)